<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catterpillers of this nation anatomized, in a brief yet notable discovery of house-breakers, pick-pockets, &amp;c. together with the life of a penitent high-way-man, discovering the mystery of that infernal society : to which is added, the manner of hectoring &amp; trapanning, as it is acted in and about the city of London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8926</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 732:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catterpillers of this nation anatomized, in a brief yet notable discovery of house-breakers, pick-pockets, &amp;c. together with the life of a penitent high-way-man, discovering the mystery of that infernal society : to which is added, the manner of hectoring &amp; trapanning, as it is acted in and about the city of London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4, 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.H. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Social life and customs --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CATTER PILLERS Of this NATION ANATOMIZED, In a Brief yet Notable Diſcovery of Houſe-breakers, Pick-pockets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Life of a penitent High-way-man, diſcovering the Myſtery of that Infernal Society.</p>
            <p>To which is added, the manner of <hi>HECTORING</hi> &amp; <hi>TRAPANNING,</hi> As it is acted in and about the City of LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M.</hi> H. at the <hi>Princes Armes</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:95468:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95468:2"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>KNavery of late is ſo epidemically practiſed, as that there is hardly a livelihood to be had without; 'tis honeſty now that beggars men: honeſty put to any occupation, may ſerve now as a fit Epithite, either for <hi>fooliſh,</hi> or <hi>breaking:</hi> Therefore it is, that we now ſee moſt in this latter non-age to wear the garment of <hi>knavery,</hi> as being <hi>ala mode,</hi> and lay aſide the good old faſhion of <hi>honeſt dealing.</hi> Our fore-fathers that wore <hi>Trunk-breeches,</hi> indeavoured to keep within them <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> by tying them with a <hi>Point</hi> of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; but alaſs, we let them out at the knees of our <hi>all-wide-breeches,</hi> not reſerving eithre Religion or Conſcience, hardly any thing that is good: So that it amazeth me to think, what (in a ſmall time) will become of this deplorable Nation. Every man doth that which is good in his own eyes, deſpiſing Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (but what is of their own making) and rejecting Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Some by deadneſs of Trade, are taught to play the knave ſooner then otherwiſe they would; others having nothing to live on, (either by ſequeſtration, &amp;c.) ſtill retain a noble and high mind, and ſo by taking ill courſes, make uſe of their wit to keep up their former gallantry. So that theſe times have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd men to ſuch a condition, that they can hardly live without diſhoneſty, only there is this difference, ſome doe it more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, others more publickly. As for thoſe that have a cloak to palliate their knavery, I ſhall paſſe by in ſilence, (as moſt Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) for I think there is hardly a Corporation in the City, in which Mr. <hi>Knave</hi> hath not been Maſter, Warden, and Aſſiſtant; nay, ther's ſcarce a ſhop which he hath not viſited. The Lawyer hath found out a trick to teach the Law how to cheat both Plaintiff and Defendant: The Souldier knows how to ſtifle Conſcience, and fight for old <hi>Nick</hi> for pay:
<q>
                  <l>Thus theſe two differ, Red-coats and Black gowns,</l>
                  <l>Th' one takes Angels, th' other takes up Crowns.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95468:3"/>The flattering Sycophant, for a little pelfe, may be hired to write Panagiticks and Encomiums of grim <hi>Pluto,</hi> and his ſutty-fac'd Wife <hi>Proſerpina.</hi> The informing Catch-pole to get money will (if a man ſpeak againſt the <hi>Pope his holineſs</hi>) inform againſt him, by vainly aſcribing it to his Highneſs; if he chance to pry into any book, he minds not ſo much the Authors intent or meaning, as how to make it ſeditious, or ſcandalous, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting what is ſpoken of ſome mechanick Trrdeſman to be meant of ſuch a Grandee. The Taſter hath learn'd a trick of the Devil, to mingle with two pound of Tobacco half a pound of Clots-foot, and ſell it for three pipes two-pence; his Cans have their bottoms almoſt in the middle, and can fill his flaggons with froth by <hi>frigging</hi> the tap; he is very buſie to carry away cans half full, and bring full ones in their room; and if for the riddance of his liquor he chance to be drunk, it may help him to miſreckon the better. Cruel Creditors, that under pretence of getting their own, do rather ſeek to ſatisfie their malice by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning and undoing their worthleſs Debtors, on the other ſide, the politick Bankrupt almoſt ruines all his Creditors, either by voluntary breaking, that thereby he may compound, or elſe go to priſon and cheat them of all, knowing well, that it is but feeing his Keeper, and the reſt of the Officers, and he may board (as in the Fleet) lie in handſome Chambers, and may have ſo much liberty, as meeting his Creditors in the ſtreet may laugh at them; he may live as voluptuouſly as he pleaſe, and all this is done at his Creditors coſt. Many more private villanies and abuſes I might unſtrip, but then I ſhall have no room to ſpeak of thoſe miſcreants, that act their rogueries more publickly, which are the Catterpillars of this Nation, corroding Cankers, that eat oftentimes ſo far into mens eſtates and lives, as that thereby they are the undoing of many Families; now becauſe I intend ſhortly a large diſcourſe, which ſhall be as an Epitome of all the villains and their villanies committed in this Nation, I ſhall therefore at preſent give you but an eſſay of ſome of them, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Ken-Miller</hi> or Houſe-breaker, the <hi>Filer</hi> or <hi>Cloyer (alias)</hi> a common Theif, the <hi>Bung-Nibber</hi> or Cut-purſe, the <hi>Hector</hi> or Knight of the Blade, with his <hi>Rum-Mort</hi> or Doxie, and laſtly, the <hi>Cafe-Pad</hi> or Knight of the Road; of the former I ſhall give you but a breif relation, that I may inſiſt the longer on the laſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95468:3"/>
               <head>Of the <hi>Ken-Miller</hi> or Houſe-breaker.</head>
               <p>THeſe Rogues have a Society among themſelves, over which they have a Principal, or Preſident, which placeth and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth every one in his ſeveral function, every one according to his ability either of wit or of ſtrength. When they enterpriſe any robbery, they conſider the difficulty thereof, or facility, and ſo do accordingly go more or leſs in company: The firſt thing they do, is an Oath they take to be faithful one to the other, to aſſiſt each other being in priſon, and if any one be taken, not to reveal the reſt. The next thing they take into conſideration, is the ſtrength of the houſe, what bolts, what locks, what doores, what weak windows; if they can force none of theſe, and they know there's a rich prize in the houſe, then they indeavour to ſeduce ſome ſervant of that houſe into their party; if that fail, they often convey an <hi>Hobgoblin</hi> (as they call him) in ſome Cask to Trunk, who (when there's a fit occaſion) lets them all in to perpetrate their work: they uſually carry about little boys with them, which being able to creep into a ſmall hole, do often facilitate their way. When they rob a houſe, they uſually are diſguiſed, and for fear of a ſurpriſe, they gagg the mouths of all the houſhold, tying them in ſuch manner, as they may neither ſtir nor cry out. Now ſince I can give you no certain note by which you may know theſe Rogues, for they know not one the other any otherwiſe then by acquaintaince, (though ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the contrary) I ſay, all the advice I ſhall give you is, truſt not too much (<hi>lowre</hi> or <hi>mint</hi>) wealth in your own houſe, but if you do, let not your ſervants know of it, for there are few <hi>(Kens mild)</hi> houſes broken open, wherein ſome ſervant of that houſe is not an actor. In the next place ſee the <hi>(Giers jack'd)</hi> doores at night lockt, your ſelf keeping the keys, which will not only in part prevent Theeves from coming in, but hinder your ſervants from gadding out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Filets</hi> or <hi>Cloyers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeir office is to frequent ſhops, pretending to buy ſeveral Commodities; now while the ſhop-keeper is buſie in reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95468:4"/>down his Ware, in the mean time he cleanly conveys ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what into his codpiece, after this, diſliking either the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or price, takes leave, and ſoon finds <hi>Stallin-kens</hi> to vend his ſtoln goods in. Some have the impudence to ſlip a piece of rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or gold buttons into their ſleeve, looking a man in the face the while. Some of them are ſo ventrous, as in a Goldſmiths ſhop to ſwallow a gold Ring, or any thing elſe that will but ſlip down, to prevent the ſevereſt ſearch, in caſe they are ſuſpected: And indeed they ſeldome enter a ſhop, in which they make not their markets before they depart. In the night they ſtand in ſome by place, and ſnatch off hats from the heads of thoſe that paſſe by, ſometimes cloaks; at other times they will (when they ſee but a ſilly boy in a Godlſmiths ſhop) blow out the candle, and ſo catch what they can: If he chance to eſpy a <hi>(Ioſeph)</hi> cloak, hang in a ſhop any thing likely to be <hi>fil'd,</hi> it will go hard if it eſcape him, neither ſhall any thing elſe that they can but touch with their bird-lime fingers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a <hi>Bung-nibber</hi> or Cut-purſe.</head>
               <p>OF this ſort there be as many women as men, eſpecially Whores, who when they are <hi>wapping</hi> will be ſure to geld the mans pocket: they are excellent good at <hi>Hocus,</hi> for can they put in a mans pocket but a middle and a fore-finger, and ſay, paſſe, <hi>Praeſto,</hi> be gone, the devil a farthing remains in his pocket; a Watch they will ſerve in the ſame manner: But before they <hi>nib a bung</hi> they jog the pocket, either to know whether there be any money there, or to jumble it all into one corner thereof, that they may make but one diving: when trading is bad with them, two or three of them will breed a quarrel in the ſtreet, &amp; when there's a great company gathered of gaping ſpectators, then take they the opportunity to <hi>fibb</hi> and <hi>eloy.</hi> Their Exchange is <hi>Tyburne,</hi> or any great Show, but eſpecially <hi>Bartholmow-fair;</hi> in this laſt to tell how many pockets were pickt, I doubt 'twill almoſt out-paſſe Arithmetick, my reaſon is, by reaſon that Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pockets of late are ſo much increaſed: Theſe of late have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd their Trade ſince gold buttons on Cloaks have been in faſhion, which they will cut off from behind, nay they will cut off even the very taſſels of ſilver Hatbands, thus they play at ſmall games rather then ſit out.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95468:4"/>
            <head>A NEW DISCOVERY OF THE <hi>HIGH-WAY THEIVES. BEING</hi> A ſeaſonable advice of one lately converted from them, to Gentle-men and Travellers to avoid their Villany, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="book">
               <div type="prologue">
                  <head>THE PROLOGUE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey who look either for a fine phraſe, or a ſublime lofty ſtile from me, will come as far ſhort of their expectation, as he that ſeeks for happineſſe in this tranſitory World; my theame and my aime being onely truth, not curioſity, makes me ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther induſtrious to benefit by Inſtruction, then pleaſant by delighting the fancy with Rhetorique; But as my miſcarriages have rendered me odious in my own, ſight, ſo in fincerity I ſhall endeavour to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95468:5"/>make my ſelf hatefull in the eyes of my miſdemeanor, by ſhewing its nakedneſſe to the World, that ſo I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> may alſo abominate me, and Inveterate enmity rend our late amity to a perpetuall diſcord, and I become an example to others to ſtear their action by a ſcale of pitty, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, expoſe them as it did me to the greateſt exigent Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, which divine providence having ſnatched me from I intended by its aſſiſtance to become a friend to my Country, by being an enemy to my late Company and Courſes, which were obnoxious and exorbitant, which when I embraced in the armes of an undaunted reſolution, I thought thoſe my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt courſes legitimate, and far more noble then the eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed babe of baſeneſſe, and ſneaking way of borrowing, arguing thus though inconſiſtent with honour, that it was far better taking of a purſe by violence from a ſtranger, then borrowing not Intending to pay, and ſo with a complement to rob my Friends, and familiar acquaintance, when the former was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually-repay'd by the Country being loſt on the Rode, ſo that many were better able to beare, contributing to my wants, then one or two, or a few: when and to which I neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, nor with a thouſand oaths ſware to repay them, as they that borrow moſt uſually do: thus I was, and others are, poor wretches deluded by Sathan, who tels the Quarrellor that to affront a meek Man is noble, and the Envious, that revenge is ſweet, repreſenting ſin in its falſe-dreſſe, that ſo it may neither be unpleaſing to the Cautious, nor terrible to the Fearfull, but conformable to every diſpoſition.</p>
                  <p>But the better to ſtifle and overcome theſe temptations, let us conſider firſt that every action hath its proper end, if it be good, the end will be anſwerable, for the end though it come laſt, it is firſt propoſed, and guideth the whole courſe, thence it is that I giving the raines of my actions to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, had well-nigh ended in deſtruction here, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> a greater hereafter, theſe ſerious thoughts hereof in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> a conviction on my conſcience, that the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be happy, becauſe there remaineth ſome thing to come after it, which the ſpirit of truth ſaith is death, the due wages of ſin, and it is want of the thoughts of the end, that makes the end
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95468:5"/>of ſo many, wretched; The Epicure thinks the only means to make him happy is to indulge to ſenſuality, and pleaſures taken up at any rate, and the Drunkard imagines it conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in aboundance of wine, like <hi>Bonoſus,</hi> of whom it was ſaid, he was not born to live, but lived to loſſe a pot, who being out-drank by one, he looked on it as an infamy, and therefore hanged himſelf for vexation, of whom it was then ſaid in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, there hangs a Tankard, and no man, here is the way, and the end.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that after an expiration of life, there is another being to be expected, an eternal ſtate, the happineſs or wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe whereof conſiſts in the former conſideration, a due weighing, that all our actions Centurin a good end, which end it an eternall ſtate, the conſequence of this opened my eyes to ſee the vanity of my villany and youthfull exorbitancies; In ſo much that true conviction of ſpirit, and no ſelf end, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt, or hope of favour hath prompume on to this diſcovery, but my wounded conſcience that makes me feare the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a Deity, more then death, knowing in my retired thoughts, that it's my duty towards God, and my Country, to un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould thoſe ſecrets that may ruine violence, and preſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ocencie, I ſhall therefore unlock the door, and ſhew you the deceiveing ways, acts and offences of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Councels, being of that horrid nature, that they deſerve the puniſhment both of body and ſoul.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> An abſolute Defiance of all thoſe that follow my former lewd Courſes.</head>
                  <p>NOW you lycentious Rebels that would be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Knights of the Road, I deteſt your actions, for which I have ſhewed my reaſon before, I begin my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, then ſince your deceite muſt be divulged, pluck
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95468:6"/>of your falſe Beards, Vizards, Hoods, Pacches, Wens, Mufflers, and falſe Perriwigs, all unnaturall, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe other diſguiſes, that obſcure the due proportion of your faces, that I may make known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world and let them ſee, whether you poſſeſs ſo much grace as may make you bluſh at the repetition, of the vileneſs of your ways, the w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I fear you want, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> conjecture ariſeth by the experience of my own former hardneſſe of heart when it was my own caſe; which in ordinate graceleſsneſſe I ſo much commiſerate in my mind, that I could with joy depoſite my blood to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate your tranſgreſſion &amp; that they might be no more; but ſound reaſon tells me I may be far more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious in ſerving of my native nation if I live, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them your baſeneſſe and inſtructing them how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the danger of the ſame, that ſo Travellers may be ſecure and ſuch as have an inclining fancy to your practice may by the unworthineſſe of the art be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from a cloſure with your wickedneſſe, who ever therefore caſts an affectionate eye upon this high-way baſeneſſe as a courſe belonging to a Gentleman, ſhews himſelfe to be ignoble, and is certainly blind, it being clearely ſpeculative to every diſcerning eye as not only baſe in it ſelfe, but infamous in its end, which ought to be regarded in every undertaking. It is in part admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that a Gentleman by birth and education deſtituted of means and action too, may by the haughtineſſe of his ſpirit be lifted up to diſdain, want as a Tyrant, that may through its oppreſſion make him rebell, &amp; ſo cauſe him to attempt this art though void of honour, when no nobler an imployment preſents him with a maint'nance, but now when imployments in the ſports of Mars his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95468:6"/>fiery blowes affords both maintenance and honour in the excerciſe of armes, againſt our nations foes, 'tis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore becomming them though ſtained in their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to indeavor their by the dends of martiall power to ſnatch the wreath of honour out of victorys hands in the feild of proud <hi>Belona,</hi> then in diſgrace and infamy to beſot their ſpirits in the armes of wanton <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> at home, though I am duopoly ſenſible that the major part of the profeſſors of this miſtery &amp; villany, are ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently apt to glory in that which truly is their ſhame, ſuppoſing themſelves to be the beſt of men who are the worſt of villains, becauſe they are ſtiled Captains &amp; Leivtenants by the drawers of the Inns when its likely they are but lately roſe from that doglike life of lackyes like the fool that is proud of his own wit, becauſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in diriſion Ironically ſaies he is wondrous wiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Oath every young Theife takes when he is admitted into the brother-hood, with other the Orders at the inveſtation of him with that honour of one of the Knights of the Road.</head>
                  <p>MOſt diſconſolate is the ſtate of that man, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leives not that their is a God, but for more wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched is his condition that knowing and believing there is a diety, ſhall un-God in his minde &amp; to himſelfe the Trinity, by worſhiping the Divel, and mens actions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95468:7"/>beſt ſpeakeing their hearts, we may conclude of thoſe that they are all diabolichall, all having erred, &amp; there is none righteous no not one, for ſearing that their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions were not ſinfull enough to conjoyne a oneneſſe between them and the Diver, this is their practice at their firſt admittance they confer an Oath of ſuch ſoul ſtuſſe, as if with more then a threefould cord, which is not eaſily broken, they would old themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by their perjury, like him, that ſweares to be true to falſhood (which implyes an impoſſibility) by reading a charge of ſecrecy that what ever misfortune happens to cloud their freedom by rendering them as a object to Juſtice and the Law, they ſhall conceal their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices to the death, or againſt any other jeopardy what ſo ever, burying in oblivion not onely his confederates, but alſo the manner of his enterance into that accurſed way, and further they proceed to ſwear him, that if the Judge ſhould further preſſe you on to a diſcovery of particulars, then you muſt cunningly creare ſome men in your fancy, deviſing not onely names but to each man a particular feature, as ſuch a beard, ſuch a hoſe, ſuch eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finding, to each a dwelling and poſſeſſion; provided you be fure to place them at a diſtance far enough, and then before inquiry be made, the danger of your triall will be paſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may be your pretended diſcovery may purchaſe favour from the bench for diſcovering of ſuch a one as was never thought on before; now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f you are examined why and now you fell into theſe courſes; you muſt tell them that you came up to <hi>London,</hi> or ſome other eminent place, with an intent to go to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but before you could provide your ſelfe, you had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95468:7"/>ſpent all your money, here ſetching a great ſigh, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very, ſad confeſſing that neceſſity conſtraining you to it to ſupply your wants, you ſell into theſe wicked courſes, which will make them think you are a poor young man newly drawn aſide, and ſo cauſe them to take pity of your condition; then muſt you promiſe never to commit the like offence: but if their mercy extend to the remiſſion of your guilt, it ſhall not onely wreſt you from the due puniſhments of the Law, but from the proſecution of your paſt evills, that ſo as you eſcape the one, you will alſo forſake the other, this is the onely way being in jeopardy to acquit you from thoſe afflictions incident to the like offences by the juſtice of an imparciall Law, &amp; by theſe means you wil not only qualify the guilt of it, but have liberty to fall to your old courles, nor muſt conſcience trouble you, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with every impiety, and glory in the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities; thus in all kind of goodneſſe they are ſlack, but apt and readily prone to do evil with a kind of eagerneſs and delight, having reſolved to grow old in the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite practice of vice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The order preſcribed, or the charge gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the eldeſt Thiefe; to the reſh before they attempt.</head>
                  <p>AS every proceeding hath its aime and end, ſo hath then undertakings its aime to do evil, to rob and ſteal, &amp; to ſpone the innocent, its end to conviction and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95468:8"/>puniſhment and theſe to extreames alſo, its meane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of carriage for being admitted, &amp; that admittance graced or rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſatiated in villany, they receive thoſe precepts that may advantage their deſigned wickedneſs; for Satan having led them by the hand unto that place which experience concludes as moſt commodious for their purpoſe, they retire and lie in wait in ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place moſt advantagious and leaſt ſuſpitious, which yeilds the eie the proſpect of the road, to ſtrictly view the booties, that others misfortunes may enrich their's, and the honeſt mans loſſe be their gain, and then the oldeſt Theif as they repaire to their ſtations pleads the precepts of his experience, and as an arch Ingen of the Divel, drawes every advantage that may promote his cauſe to the longeſt extent in this due order follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yee that are ſworn Knights of the road be ruled by me, whoſe long experience makes me able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and my love to you willing to inſtruct you, thus muſt you place your maskes and chin cloath &amp; fit it at a moment to diſguiſe your faces, thereby to blind the intellects of ſuch as by conſtraint pay tribute to your wants, who then can know &amp; with conſiderat heed directly ſwear you are the men, when theſe artificiall vizards, are withdrawn, &amp; ſo the viſible tokens vaniſh that might informe mens knowledge what you are, and that your words may have a different ſound, after the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance of your ſpeech by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in your mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, that ſo as your habit, face &amp; hair obſcure your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, your ſpeach reputed undiſguiſable, may darken and not give light to your diſcovery, &amp; then ingeniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrive a warch word to your ſelves that may occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no ſuſpicion, as whats a Clock, a queſtion common
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95468:8"/>in almoſt every mouth, which being named, let every man fall to his proper work, thoſe that are ſtrongeſt at the graſp, let them ſeiſe firſt, always duly obſerving this, to catch the bridle with your left hand, and with the right, ſeiſe on your ſword, for your juſt guard, and if they do reſiſt, the one prevents their ſlight, the other cuts his courage, the weaker ſort whoſe charge is to bid ſtand, and ſo confront the Horſes head, preſent them with a piſtoll fit for to diſcharge, if they deny deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their purſe, ſo that either by conſent, if not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, inforce them to yeild.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The manner of their aſſault, with their Courage in and after the Action.</head>
                  <p>THus being in redineſſe, let one cry arme, arme my Comrades. Whilſt he is talking thus, a prize comes by or in their ſight, if up the Hill they meet him, if down, they bid you follow cloſe at their heeles, where each having ſingled out his choice, which he likes to deale with, the coaſt being cleare, they fall up to their cloſe order, and ſide by ſide they joyntly ſeiſe their prize, where ſometims the baſeneſſe of ſome ſpirits, make them unworthy of what they are, men; for when nature hath beſtowed the full proportion of their limbs, to make them of the largeſt manly ſize, yet ſo baſe is their ſpirts, ſo different are the qualities of men, that no ſoonerthe word deliver is let looſe, but they are ſuppriſed ſo with fear, that like babes, they cry and tremble before there is any weapon drawn to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright them, and of times their purſes are as poor as their courages, which makes theeves reſolute and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95468:9"/>to the like attempts again, when occaſion offers a tryall, but then on the contrary, to their praiſe, I ſpeak it, that ſome in compariſon to thoſe baller men, are pignies, yet of ſo undaunted reſolution and unreſiſtible courage, that neither threats of death or torture can dull the edges of their couragious ſpirits, but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they'l yeild to men, they'l ſtoop to death; but when power and might ſubdues them to the Rob bers baſeſt will, then they with-draw unto a ſecret place, and ſearch the ſecret parts where money uſe to lye, with ſo ſtrict care, that ſooner may they quoine, then ſave one peny for their need, where if they find ſome gold by chanes, quilted for more ſecurity, they call them Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, and diſhoneſt men, becauſe they ſeek to ſave what is their own, which they call couſonage, at which the poor Traveller cryes he is utterly undone, becauſe he loſes then his whole eſtate, and by his meanes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to move their ſtony hearts, but it is impoſſible to mollify thoſe Flints with teares, or move thoſe Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants with ſighs or groanes, whoſe conſciences ſleep faſt in villany, never moved at a poor mans loſſe or ſtraits, but prompt for the deſire of unlawfull gain, to act the parts of fiends not, men; nor doth your baſeneſs centur in thoſe wrongs, but higher ſwell, oft-times ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing horſes with a jeſt, that it's no robbery, deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately ingaging them thus rob'd, to ſweare they ſhall not follow you by hew and cry, or by means of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral riſing of the towns adjacent; and ſo robbed, tifled, and amazed you leave them wrapt in woes, and haſte away to ſecure your ſelves where every Crow that flies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts a fear, and every Calfe or Coult that ſtirs or makes the buſhes ruſh, ſeems to your fearfull fanſie, a Conſtable to apprehend you for your theft, which ſets your wits upon the tenters of the moſt ſevereſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igents, I ſpeak not at a giuſſe, but what I know, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95468:9"/>lately when a Robbery was done, a ſtrong confuſion roſe by ſo ſmall means, as cannot but engage the ſerious to admire the timerity of their dejected mindes, for an Owle who to gaine ſhelter from the troubles of the uncouth days, when all the ayery tribe wandering, flock to him, ſcreen'd now in the obſcure retired reſidence of a hollow tree, no ſooner was he got into his den, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween diſcontent and joy, he ſeemd to rend his hollow reſidence with fatall whoops, and much amazing ſcreeks which infuſed ſuch a terror in their diſtruſtfull minds, that whips, ſwitches and ſpurs were ſet on furious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe to out-ſpeed the wind in their quick flight, for fear thoſe hollows were voices of the Countrey men, following them in their great haſty ſpeed to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, thus doth a continuall fear attend their motion; Inſomuch that they fear very ſhadow of themſelves, till ſome by Inn, afford; a ſhelter to your baſeneſſe, where you fall to a diviſion of your ſpoyles, but here you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in your colours, by acting a cheat to your Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and play the double Thieves, firſt rob honeſt men, and chen your ſelves, with bloody oaths cheating your boſome friends, reſerving the beſt part unto your ſelves, from thoſe you date abuſe, and to defend your juſtneſſe, dam your ſelves to the laweſt region of the worſt of places: thus have I often found your perjury; ſad it is to do wickedly, but moſt deſperate to load on ſin, with the weight of another.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The unbleſſedneſs of their gaines, and how ſoon they ſpend what they thus unlawfully get.</head>
                  <p>THat which is founded on an unjuſt and unſound, principall, can have no good or ſubſtanciall being or continuance, and that which is purchiſed by fraud
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95468:10"/>and deceit is waſted as likely with a blaſt, as it was got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unjuſtly with abuſes, ſo that it marers not whether it be little or much that is goten, ſince the quality de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the quantity being purchaſed with ſin and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that ſin died with blood, and as ſaith the proverb, il-goten goods never proſpers, nor can they ever thrive who like rowling ſtones, are alwaies moving from place to place, but as the divel was your frined in enterpriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your wretched act, ſo are you his veſſels in ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in adoration of him what you have gained, ſo that to have much is to as little purpoſe, as for a man to thatch his dwelling houſe with ſnow which the beames of <hi>Phabus,</hi> diſſolves in drops, for Inns and Taverns, thoſe common ſincks of ſin, that know our wicked waies in larg our biles to ſink our coin in their unboſomed pouches, who knowing our wicked waies preſume we dare not cavile, leaſt all prove ill for us, ſo that if right conſidercd we rob for them not for our ſelves, and as with ſin we purchaſed what we had, ſo they with couſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age rob us, leaving remedileſſe our wrongs that live by fraud, to make them ſwim in wealth, ſo thrifty is their way that on the ruins of the country they do ſubſiſt, wch makes them rich in plenty, as we penurious through our want of coin ſpent in exceſſe; for ſome I know who had a trible part of all we gained, as being Maſter of us all, and yet his gaines oftimes came ſhort to countervaile his for'ſt expence and prodigality, yet was he wary if I truly veiw him in his ſtation, leſt too much vapouring ſhould occaſion ſuſpition, whence I conclude that want of a bleſſing on our continuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> trade, which is accurſed, made all to vaniſh as if it had never been, he only ſuffering us to rain till we were fit for the ſcourge of his wrath, who ſpares long to ſee if grace will work its proper end, converſion: as ever bleſſed be his name it hath on me, but if in ſtead of contrition, there appeare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95468:10"/>neſſe of heart, then God, lets looſe Juſtice to execute due vengence on the actors of ſuch helliſh deeds: Firſt apprehenſion, next impriſonment, then conuiction then laſt of all, to conclude the tragicall enterlude of your exorbitances, comes the period of your life by a ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death which the law extracts as a due debt we owe to Juſtice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>BOOK II.</hi> Hearty diſſwaſions with my beſt indeavours to reclaim them.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The miſery of an impriſoned eſtate, which muſt be the firſt ſtep of ſatisfying the Law.</head>
                  <p>LIberty, that rich inheritance of all that are born to live, and live to dye, as it is the ſweeteſt of injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment next that imperiall gem of health, ſo the want thereof, next to ſickneſſe, muſt needs be of all other the moſt bitter, ſince then to be confined unto the confines of a Jaile is to be in part unmand what and how great is that wretchedneſſe that is occaſioned by a want not onely of liberty, but a continuall dread of a ſhamefull death, and that made more terrible by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable expectation of an eternall impriſonment, where there is weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing, of Teeth with flames of unquenchable fire for ever more; for like the pitcher that though it go often to the wel, yet comes it broken home at laſt, othen forſake this liſe, leſt the priſon become your Inn, and the terrour of that place ful of tortures are ſo exſaſperated by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agination of a noble mind, that hell it ſelf cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more exquiſite woes &amp; pains, a continuance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of weare ſufficient to puniſh all offences, if the law diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with that debt due to Juſtice the life of the offenders: for you no ſooner enter here but a thouſand
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95468:11"/>vices in a hundred licentious wretched ſoules ſurround you, where ſighing is their ayr, their comfort coldneſſe, and their food diſpair, &amp; when the keeper with the grim aſpect of his ſtern cuntenance makes you tremble with the fear of a new marterdom, whilſt the inſulting raſcal on the tiptoes of his prid, ſcrews his il-favored face to a ſtern frown, which ſo dejects the ſpirit of the impriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſlaves, that the contrition of their looks ſeemes to implore his ſmiles whoſe diviliſh heart having renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed remorſe caſts a deſiance in their pitious face, and not there unquiet hours onely do taſt the gall of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but the ſweet minuts of their reſt, if that rude place afford them any, are frighted with your cares or ſome rude noiſe of beaſtly creatures from whoſe drunken voices comes unwelcome ſounds, oaths, curſing the Stars, the Earth, and all thats repreſented to his thoughts blaſpheming God, banning Angels, and their creditors, reviling fate, in that he is heire only to fortuns frowns, and to be ſure, if onely a ſinal ſpark of wickedneſs came with him to this worldly hel, you accompliſh the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt exigent of ſhame before you come to ſhake hands and part, and grow a ſubtile Artiſt in the Divels Trade of ſin. Moſt in conſiſtant then is the found practice of the vulgar ſort who ſay, a priſon will reclaim the faults of youth, when tis moſt true they do precipitate their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter over throw, for ill exſamples purge not ſin, but adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the will that is pron to foly, ſo that the priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners living deaths are feeling moniments of wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and yet are only prologues to thoſe tragedies, your over throws record in characters of blood this will inſtruct you what it is to dy not unto nature, but far worſe to a perpetuall infamy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95468:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> By ſhewing them how much they are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in other Mens opinions of them.</head>
                  <p>MEN may be witty yet not wiſe, ſubtile yet not diſcreet, as it fareth with moſt of you, who think, though vainly, that by attempting deeds ignoble will purchaſe you eſteem, renown, and honour in the popular, vulgar eye, as if to act baſe villany were the way to be admired, not ſcorned, as though the actions you have done, are ſuch as have contracted amity with honour, and ſo engaged Men in Authority to protect your lives, that in deſpite of Law you muſt ſurvive; ſo from the Jayle unto the gallows, in a preſumptuous ſafety you are ſent careleſſe of danger, where juſtice tels you your conceits are vain, as are your lives, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and ungodly trade, for men whoſe judgments ſtear by piety, juſtly condem your ſin, and pitty you for charity, not your deſert, and ſince my ſincere inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour hath thus diſcovered you and your diſguiſe, beſure they I know your tricks to well to be entrapped by you, ſince your fained worths are obvious cheats, and faint prorectors of your wickedneſs, ſeace, and give over thoſe acts of fiends not men, which makes you as much the effigies of Sathan, as God created you the Image of Himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> By putting them in mind of their wicked and curſed ends, (which they fondly and fooliſh: ly jeſt at, as alſo their reward in the world to come.</head>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95468:12"/>
                  <p>GOD concludes him curſed, and man moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably wretched that hangs upon a Tree, which beſides the ſhame that attends you and your poſterity, the death it ſelf might with the curſedneſs of it, diſſwade you to put a period to the practiſe of that great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in which conſiſts the violation of a command, and ſo a breaking of the whole Law, neither dyes not your ſhame with your body, but your Family though never ſo Noble, ſuffers a wrent in their honour, by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcipating of the Infamy you ſuffer, which for ſome ages reſt dyed with ſcandall, although never ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of the crime, &amp; yet thoſe ſenſleſſe Catiffes who inherit this death by their tranſgreſſions, laugh at this heavy curſe, as at a ſport, and call it pleaſure to be pluck to heaven in a ſtring, and thus by the power of Sathan are they prompt onwards to laugh at their own ruine, whilſt what affrights others with an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of horror, doth rather move them with a kind of pleaſing joy to delight themſelves, who think the more they become conformable to the Divel, the nearet they approached happineſ, but the ſame weakneſs that leads you on in confidence to thoſe ſo groundleſs hopes, may prompt you one ſtep farther to preſume, as I found mercy, ſo may you from God and men, I wiſh to you the glorious grace I found, but pray conſider a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, cannot Compoſe a general, one Swallow makes no ſummer, &amp; know that if mercy did extend to wave heavens and earths wrath from me, yet grace twice offended, tribles the vengeance of a ſevere juſt Judg, and for your ſufferings here by death, that's but a raſt of thoſe highly birrer and ever laſting ſorrows that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſtore, for ſuch as defile their lives with ſo great ſinne, as makes heaven execute the heat of wrath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95468:12"/>wrath, as the due merit of your hainous ſin; which to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, thereis onely one mesnes left, and that's contrition; if there remain yet any ſparks or likelihood of grace, though but ſo much as may occaſion one good thought: and if that unto ſin you have not made a laſting league of ſervitude, behold your fact with a relenting eie of pity: thereby to purchaſe eaſe and comfort to your ſad diſparing ſouls: then happie men, not that you have been baſe, but that from ſin you have retired the ſanctity. Times never paſt to mend, better late then never; for he that delights to perſevere in ſin, not being able ro appeal to Chriſt, and to his merits, but with a willing greedineſſe laies hold on his damnation. And if no ſence of things ſecular can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict thoſe hardned hearts, if not a temporal, yet an eternal death muſt needs move ſence of danger; the one is but breath, the other endleſſe everlaſting pain, which ere it be ended is ſtill renewed in burning lakes of brimſtone that never die, but burn with cruel tortures for each hainous ſin; where howls and hollow grones adds to the eternal weight of miſery; when froſts, fires, drownings, ſulphur, and other the worſt of puniſhment attend their wretched ſoules: this is the ſad period of your waies, which if it work not it's deſired end, pleceaſe to labour to perſwade you more. But on the contrary, if I cannot convert you, I could willingly convict you: and here I could name both you, and your abode, but that you have no conſtant reſidence, but for a night in ſome by-road, and ſo away, either into the Weſt, or North, or ſometimes into the South: And as your dwellings you change, ſo do you every day your names; ſo that in ſhape, in being, place and name, you change with every day, like the mutable <hi>Camelcon,</hi> but never into white Innocency: And thus to inform, were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95468:13"/>but to put in doubt the Inquiſitive, and not at all in lighten to your due apprehenſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> An Ingenuous diſcovery of them to each diſcerning eye, by infallible tokens how to know them on the Road, and if robbed, how ſurely to track them.</head>
                  <p>THe uncertainty of your attire, and various diſguiſes, with your non-reſidence, and changable names, makes me uncapable to do what I would; therefore I wil do what I can, and in every lineament ſo pourtract you and your carriages to every man that ſcriouſly ſhal peruſe this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, that with eaſe, not difficulty, he may know you as you ride, and by that meanes inable him to provide for his own ſecurity; or if by you robb'd, let him but obſerve my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and he need not queſtion to apprehend you, when your ſences of danger is paſt, and you in your thoughts ſecure. You ſhall have it may be two or three of them overtake you, &amp; pretend if they fear'd your ſtrength, that they were lately affronted in the Wood by eight or ten ſtout fellows; but they beat the rogues, and made them Hie to ſave themſelves, and ſeal this with ſtrong oathes, and by your anſwer ſound your ſpirits whether valiant or no; which if they find apt to be danted; then they wait an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to act their roguery on you; and it may be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they boaſt in drink, what they have done to others, as now to you; and as a reward for what unwillingly you lend to them, they'l pretend to give you a word that ſhall protect you from the like affront again far better then your ſword; as, <hi>Round-de-la-vera-hay, The Moon ſhines bright,</hi> or the like; but theſe are chears, and no ſecuring powers:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95468:13"/>It's true, when we were ready to ſeiz a prize, &amp; ſpi'd a friend, or other company coming near, we uſed ſome ſuch words, to bid our company forbear a while for our own ſafeties ſake, which honeſt Travelers ignorant of any wrong ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing, whilſt we by theſe knew what we had to do, but elſe thoſe words we valued not, for prize and nothing elſe could ſatisfie our mindes that fought for money; therefore never believe them; but obſerve dear Country-men my better rules for your ſecurity, which for your ſakes I'le take the honeſt pains to write in plain-wiſe, not deceitfully.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>BOOK III</hi> Plain, inſtructions for the honeſt Traveller, that he may paſſe in ſafety on the way.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What he is to take heed unto before he begin his Jonrney.</head>
                  <p>DEar Countrie-men that travel on the Road, the paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of my wicked life having been conſumed in ſin, and that ſin maintained by the ſpoile of Paſſengers; I ſeeing the wretchedneſs of that ſtate, find how much I am bound to ſatisfie the debt I owe you, to the uttermoſt of my power, which reaches to no more ſatisſactory an act, then good adviſe how to avoid the dangers of the road, and what I ſpake herein is the iſſue of my long finful experience; as thus, when you carrie a charge about you, let ſecreſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal your money, and the time of your departure in your breaſt; for 'tis a cuftome no leſſe common then indiſcreet, when you undertake a journey, to blaſe that undertaking amongſt your reputed friends, who out of ſeeming love,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95468:14"/>drink healths to your good Journey, and your ſafe return; this glaſſe of friendlhip exprates the leaſt miſtruſt of wrong or thought of Ill, when by thoſe means I have often known a Son betray his Father, a Brother his Brother, &amp; one friend another; in condeſcending and complotting with ſome thievs who for his giving notice of the prize, ſhares one quarter, or more, of that gain he ſo betrays, when but for this fond humour they had not been diſcovered and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laien; and which is worſt; ſometimes you chuſe a guard to ſuccor you, and to take your part, in whom you truſt, who oſt doth bring you into danger, without the leaſt ſuſpition on your part; for when they bid you ſtand, hee'l draw as in a valiant rage, and with ſome one appointed for that uſe, hack ſwords, while anothyer threarens his leath; if he ſtand on thoſe tearms of ſeeming honour: you ſeeing his ſalſe danger fear his death, &amp; bid him yield, which he though wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſeems loth to do: nay more, he knowing wel which way they fled, will ſend the <hi>Hue and cry</hi> another way; and if you ſuppoſe you know any of them that did the robbery, and do hit right, he perſwades you, that whileſt they ſought his diſguiſe fell off, and therefore he markt him, and knows 'tis not the man, and with penſive look he will lament your bad hap: and thus your boſome friend betraies you.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How to carry themſelves in their Inns.</head>
                  <p>IT is as common a cuſtom, as a cunning policy in thievs, to place Chamberlains in ſuch great Inns where <hi>Cloathiers</hi> and <hi>Graſiers</hi> uſe to lye; and by their large bribes to infect others, who were not of their own preferring; who noting your purſes when you draw them, they'l gripe your cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bags,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95468:14"/>and feel the weight, and ſo inform the Maſter thievs of what they think, and not thoſe alone, but the Hoſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is oft as baſe as they, if it be left in charge with them all night; he to his roaring gueſts, either gives item, or ſhews the purſe it ſelf, who ſpend liberally, in hope of a ſpeedie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit: and all this is occaſioned by want of diſcretion in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging your buſineſs for the beſt; therefore be ſecret, and let little be made known to thoſe that watch to do you wrong.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Shewing the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ger of travelling on the Sabbath day.</head>
                  <p>HE that expects a bleſſing from the Father of bleſſings above, muſt ſo behave himſelf in the eyes of Heaven, whilſt on earth, that he muſt live here, as if he were there already; and the only way ſo to do, is to ſtear our actions by <hi>Gods</hi> command, which ſaith, <hi>Keep holy my Sabbath-day,</hi> in which wee ought to remember <hi>Gods</hi> reſt from labour, and reſt our ſelves from ſin; for when wee come ſhort of this, <hi>Gods</hi> love and protection goes ſo far beyond us, that wee can feel no joy in that dark night which is out of his preſence; which made <hi>Moſes</hi> ſay, Except thou O <hi>God.</hi> go along with us, let us not go hence: thence it is, that few which Travell on this day, eſcape the hands of thievs; for they know none ride at that time, but on great and urgent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and that can ſcarſe be don without great ſtore of Coin; ſo that if they once are ſeen, they ſure are robb'd imediately: and though the Countrie are in joyned to paie what you; ſhall loſe by daie, yet not on this; becauſe it is a daie of reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and as you are remedileſs being robb'd, ſo helpleſs before, for there is no Companie to aid the honeſt Traveller as at other times.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95468:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP VI.</hi> How to know a Thief from an goneſt man.</head>
                  <p>BEe ſure on the Road to aſſociate with none but ſuch as you find inclin'd rather to leave your company, then keep it; for ſuch as preſs to be near you, though againſt your will, are very dangerous: But I'le preſently inform you how to know if they be thievs or not. Take occaſion to make ſome ſtaie, then note whether they ſtaie, or keep their pace, or elſe alight and go on foot that you may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them; follow ſome halfe an hour after a ſlow pace, and if you overtake them, take heed, for that's the ſureſt ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptome of a Thief: The other uſuall marks of Thieves bee theſe, which as you ride you may diſcern ſo plain, that you need not doubt the truth of what you think. They muffle their faces with their cloaks, or elſe their cloak or coat hides all their clothes; they have a hand-kercher or ſcarfe, which with their hand they'l rear up to their eies, over their faces juſt when they bid you ſtand. And if by occaſion of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie they leav off this, that you may miſſe your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>your eie full in their face, and you ſhall ſee them turn their faces on one ſide; which if they do, then keep you diſtance, ride from them, and marke whether their face and beards agree together, &amp; are not counterfeit: and above all things ſhun him that rides in a Mountier-Cap; and ſuch as whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers oft, and are inquiſitive after your buſineſſe; or what your imployments are, for 'tis to know what you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95468:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Shewing how dangerous it is to grow familiar with any stranger upon the Way.</head>
                  <p>WHen you take your Journie whither the occaſion calls you with a friend, you paſſe not far before your companie is increaſed by a third: when there is two to one, there is no fear of him being alone, before you call him fellow-tra veller, and joie in his company, and hee in yours: but before you have rid 10 miles together on your way he overtakes ſome three more of his Company, then he ſhakes and trembles, and ſeems afraid; and cries, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly friends we are fore-laid; if ye have Charge about you, let me know't, wee'l fighr it out; if we have nought to loſe, wee were beſt yield: By theſe like words hee'l quickly finde whether the prize be rich; and whileſt you thought there had been three to three, there's four to two: If they find you armed, then one who they find fitteſt for the work, they cloath in Ruſſet, like a Country-bore, in his high-ſhoo's, with twiſts of Hay inſtead of Boots, a goad in his hand, riding aſide upon a ſaddle moade of a wiſpe of ſtraw, who rides cheek by joul with you, and cauſes mirth by his moſt ſimple talk; you not ſo much as think he is capable of hurt: but when he hath brought you into their ſnare, he ſeizes one, and your new fellow-traveller the other, the reſt come in, and then it is in vain to ſtrive, for nothing leſſe then your money will ranſome you out of their hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95468:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> How, when, and where to wide.</head>
                  <p>THoſe ſo many prodigion waies to rob the Innocent, bids every man be warie how, and when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and where: if he have any charge about him, let mee adviſe you not to ride by day, but by night; but for thoſe baſe ſheep-ſtealing punie rogues, that hazard their necks for a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I am unacquainted with their actions; therefore I do not undertake to ſhew their deceits; but for thoſe Cutters on the road, I can aſſure you, you are free from any horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whatſoever: for 'tis their rule, that ſurely none by night will ride that are worth robbing. Next, they muſt keep civill hours, for fear that through miſtruſt they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelien ded; therefore it's their chief care to take their Inn betimes? and more, they hardly dare advenuture in the dark, becauſe they cannot ſee either your dangerous defences, or their own advantages, or ſpie piſtols or other private wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: &amp; you have time your money to convey from them, and divers other advantages the day denies; but ſince this is ordained for reſt, I can ſay no more, but it's my beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to keep you from the dangers of the road: and it's a general rule with high-way-men, to keep their ſtation upon the greateſt roads, that of thoſe number which paſſe by, they may ſelect ſuch as they think are richeſt prize: but on your petty rodes, where ſearce any uſe to paſs; they never uſe to come: there you may paſſe ſecure: which I adviſe you chooſe if poſſible you can, rather then on great roads. But 'tis a fooliſh cuſtom you have gotten, when you ride by any place that commonly ſpeaks danger, you buſſle up together ſide by ſide, which is moſt commonly your overthrow:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95468:16"/>but take my counſel here, when e're you ride, in fear eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ride far aſunder, a Buts length at leaſt, and then bee ſure they will never attempt to rob you, when your ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling order will give ſome of you leave undoubtedly to eſcape, and to raiſe the Countrie in their purſuit: Beſides, their Company is ſet in ſeveral parties, when ſhould you ride in a cluſter, they will ſurely ſallie out; and ſeiz their purchaſe; when if they ſhould fall upon a ſtragling partie, before they can do any thing it's ſtrange but reſcue comes, which eaſily will make the Cutters flie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> If hee bee beſet.</head>
                  <p>I Have thus trac'd them in every <hi>meander</hi> of their ſinful courſes, whereby to diſcover them to you, that you may avoid them; it ſhall be my next work to inſtruct you how to behave your ſelf if unhappily you are beſet; Look not as if amazed about, as if you hoped for reſcue, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages them to height of reſolution; but look as ſtern as they, and ſo, as if to fear you were a ſtranger, and make your brow the throne of rage and furie; and this is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt and moſt certain way to ſave your monie, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation too; for they fighting with a guilty conſcience within, and without againſt a Countrie-Law and Juſtice, right and equitie, which I ſpeak by experience, if nobly you reſiſt, will make the moſt undaunted ſpirit of them all ſtoop to diſcouragement; for I have known them that of themſelvs have been of ſo unreſiſtable a reſolution, that they durſt out-brave the roaring Canon to the mouth, and ſcorn to ſtoop to baſceneſs; yet in this act, when men have but ſeemed to reſiſt, they have ſhook and trembled, even
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95468:17"/>to a remorſe of their wickedneſſe; for though they ſwear to ſhoot you if you yield not, 'tis but to fright you, for they dare not do it, becauſe they know that murther never eſcapes the hand of heavens juſt puniſhment, and by thus doing oftentimes Thievs may be taken, and ſo others freed by their apprehenſion from the like danger you were in, and by this act you will gain honor and repute.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> By telling them of a fault moſt Travellers are guilty of, if Thievs aſſault them.</head>
                  <p>YOur meaneſt hearts ſubmit too ſoon, and oft-times yield almoſt before they bid you ſtand, and then wiſh they may eſcape, that ſo the Hundred may repair your loſs, if they are not apprehended by the <hi>Hue and Crie,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily you oft-times ad to, and if not double the ſumm, knowing the Hundred will be glad for to compound; and ſo you cozen both the Countrie and the Thievs, and to convince them that you fought like men, you cut and flaſh your cloaths, and ſwear they did it in the fight who robb'd them; when yet ten to one your blows were tears, crying for life, and then bid them take all; but theſe ignoble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits I hate, and by my work intend no love to them, but to the nobler ſort.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95468:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> If by chance he be unawares ſurpriſed, how to behave himſelf.</head>
                  <p>BUt if by your own negligence, and the frowns of fate, the pleaſure of your Journie be eclips'd and clouded by a ſudden ſurpriſal, blame not me, who indeavour if you pleaſe to hinder thoſe accidents if you be careful, elſe the fault's your own; Yet let me ſtill adviſe you what to do if you ſee no hopes but you muſt yield, ſtrive not at all when 'tis too late, but give the faireſt words you can, racking your fineſt wits to pleaſe their ear; and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly wiſh you had more monie to ſupplie their wants, and with a kind of chearfulneſſe deliver ſome, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they'l let you paſſe without further to do; but if they make an offer, ſeem to yield freely to it: then will they ſift you ſoundly, but do not hold your hand upon your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but ſeem to be a ſtranger unto fear, and that will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their ſuſpition of a greater ſumme; for when I have took ſo much as pleaſed me well, I have by men's fear had grounds to think that they had more, and ſo by laying my hand upon their arme or thigh, or near where it lay hid, they would crie out, they were undone, when I as yet found nothing more, but by their temeritie have been incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to make a ſtricter ſearch, and found conſiderable ſums that ſecretly laie hid, when if they had been diſetect, they had been ſecure and ſafe from me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95468:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Being Robb'd, how to follow them, which way to ſet <hi>Heu-and-cry,</hi> how to coaſt, and where to find the Thievs.</head>
                  <p>IF you have loſt your wealth, their is no help; but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſurpriſe the thievs by ſtrict purſuit: therefore be wary, and follow with all ſpeed, tell you obtain your wiſh: and ſeiz the rogues that lately ſeized you. But bee carefull, as it becomes you to follow undiſcerned, leſt they lay Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcadoe to ſurprize your liberty, and it ſubdue to bonds; for if they ſee you in your chaſe, the formoſt hee'l ſlip into ſome by place, when you ſupoſe no ill, ride on: but when you do draw nigh, they ſally, and ſecure you in ſtrong bonds, where faſt bound they leav you, and then hee that comes next releaſes you; to him you tell your adverſsfates, and ſay they left the road, but whither they went you know not how to tell, but admit mee to your counſell, and I'le tell you how to ſhun their eſcape; and by example the ſureſt Shool-Maſter, I ſhall direct you what to do in this: as ſuppoſe in <hi>Coal-brook</hi>-road you loſt your purſe, the Thievs to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg</hi>-road or <hi>Stanes</hi> will ſurely ride and not fail to take up their lodging, there for that night this is moſt certain, and the ſoundeſt precept in their law, and truly for invention, the wittieſt ſecret that I er'e knew or heard, and ſtands with reaſon, therefore let reaſon guid you to ſecure theſe Thievs if they have robb'd you: for they know full well none uſe to travell from road to road: no not the <hi>Hue-and-cries</hi> they never croſſe the paſſages, but go ſtreight along; ſo that by this cloſe way they reſt at pleaſure, and are gone again before the lazy <hi>Hue and Crie</hi> ſalutes them with an alarum;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95468:18"/>nay, and with grief I ſpeak it, ſome ſilly fellow newly crept into office ſearches and enquires, and by Authoritie ſeizes poor Travellers, as far from wrong as they from wit and knowledg, thinking by this falſe apprehenſion to get cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and be eſteemed double-diligent, when they poor harmleſſe ſouls, now under hold, though free from guilt, do oft-times loſe their lives for what they never were once ſo much as privie to; therefore to regulate this errour, and that you may avoid the like, take my advice, and then I hope you'l find and ſecure the right offender: and ſo to do, with all poſſible ſpeed ſcour the next great Road, not ſtreight before, but either on the right hand, or on the left; and if you miſs them, then conclude they are ſhelter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſome Inn which you have paſt, and therefore obſerv my good advice, and you ſhall ſurely find and apprehend them, as thus; If you have miſt them, ſet ſome careful Spies with a ſufficient aſſiſtance near at hand, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident you'l ſee them come that way without the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of fear; and if (becauſe I have betraied the ſecrets of their Trade) they leav this uſe, I am ſure nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their wit, nor the Divels aſſiſtance, can ever deviſe the like again; and I ſeriouſly proteſt, I ſee no way for them to flie with ſafetie, or the leaſt hope to eſape: But this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that if they light of any conſiderable ſumme, then they rid that night to their randezvouz in the Citie of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which is too ſure a ſhelter for them; but with a real heart to fright them from that waie, who I cannot draw from it with advice, I will purſue them hither with the beſt inſtructions for their apprehenſion; but obſervantly take notice, for here is as eminent an example of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie as any ever the Divel inrich'd their knowledge with; for if you are robb'd in the Eaſtern quarter, purſue them not in the direct road to <hi>London</hi> with <hi>Hue and Crie,</hi> for by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95468:19"/>ſome other way they are fled; therefore haſt to the Citie, and in <hi>Weſtminſter, Holborn,</hi> the <hi>Strand,</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden</hi> ſearch ſpeedily, for there they are. If Northward they light on you, then to <hi>Southwark,</hi> the <hi>Bank ſide,</hi> or <hi>Lambeth</hi> they are gone, and ſo of the Weſt and South; and when you find them, ſeiz all you find, for they are all Companions that are together.</p>
                  <p>Thus they alwaies do contrive to take thoſe places where they may moſt ſeemingly be ſafe from dangers of purſuits, and in thus doing as I have ſhewed you, they think the Citie is between them and the <hi>Hue and Crie,</hi> and they ſecure; and ſo before the ſearch comes to them, as it ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome goes ſo far, they have time enough to ſtay, and then be gone. Thus have I laid ſuch a forme of Inſtructions for the <hi>Hue and Crie,</hi> as if obſerved, they cannot eſcape his hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> An extraordinary Charge the Countrie uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally put themſelvs unto, which is both needleſſe and hurtful.</head>
                  <p>CUſtome, that Mother of abſurdities, hath not only To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, but Naturalized a practice, which though well intended, is not onely unneceſſary in a diſcreet eye: but hurtfull, as ſhall bee made manifeſt; for where any robbery is committed, the Hundred commonly puts a watch imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to guard that place where it is done. Which veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the old Proverb uſed in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſion of the like acts: To ſhut
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95468:19"/>the ſtable-door when the Steed is loſt: 'tis not to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ever the Thief ſhould come to make a needleſſe breach to thank the Groom for feeding of the beaſt ſo wel, and rubbing, dreſſing, and looking to him with honeſt care: for juſt ſo it muſt needs fare with them that ſhould igno, rantly come to the ſame place where they ſeized their prize knowing this cuſtome to be in uſe, but ſay they ſhould com there, and at that time the watch is ſate; I really proteſt, I ever held that road that had a watch upon it, to be the ſureſt and beſt place for purchaſe. For firſt the honeſt Travellours ſuppoſes it impoſſible for them to be robb'd, being guarded thus, which makes him careleſſe to ſecure himſelf, becauſe they fear not; whilſt alas! the Thievs do what they liſt, and freely paſs, and the watch-men ner'e the wiſer; for they ſtand on that place commanded for their ſtation, and move not from it, when 'tis indifferent with the Thievs when he lays hold on what he looks for, his booty, which where hee ſingled it out, all places are alike to him, and ſo another's as good as that: ſo that the coaſt be clear in ſight; nd when he hath done the deed, he may ſecurely paſs the watch, who cannot diſcern or know him from another man, but lets him paſs for honeſt. For I never paſt them, but they gave me civil language: 'tis true, they bid me have a ſpecial care I was not robb'd, when in truth it was my trade to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der others: but then ſuppoſe they had examined me, I would have anſwered them with ſuch reſpect and civil lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and praiſe the work they ſtood to do, that they could not ſuſpect me; and I have known ſome of my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Cutters, that when examined, have carried themſelvs with that diſcretion, that to incourage them to be careful in their place, hath thrown twelve-pence, or a half-crown piece but newly borrowed, where they never mean to paie, that they have promiſed to drink his honeſt health. Nay,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95468:20"/>ſuppoſe they ſhould ſuſpect me and my Companie, alas! they are poor ſilly old men, that are decrepid, weak, and altogether unable to make reſiſtance, and good for nothing but to loyter there; for I have ſeen a dozen ſuch ſtand all together with Halberds, Pikes, Pitchforks, and Clubs, amazed and frighted, not daring to ſtir to reſcue them that were diſtreſs'd; whilſt we before their faces have bid men ſtand; aſſaulted, ſurpriſed, and refled ſuch as we liked; when we had done it, and were upon the gallop, then they faintly crie, Thievs, Thievs: Stop them, ſtop them; when none but Trees and Hedges that heard their clamours: and I have known ſome that by way of parly have grown familiar with them, and watcht opportunity, and ſeazed and bound them hand and foot; then in a ditch have charg'd them on their lives to lay ſo quiet that none may hear them: and then like a ſafe guard, ſet to preſerve the Travellour from wrong, with the watch-mens bills have ſtood with confidence till booty come that way, and then made bold as with authority to ſtop and hold ſuch as they think have coyn, and on pretence of ſearch for what was lately loſt upon the way: if they find purchaſe worth the takeing, ſeaz it and be gone: ſo that a watch doth hurt, not good. But if you needs will have it ſo, chooſ luſty able men, reſolved and yonug, arm them with bows and arrows, Muſkets, or good Carbines, or Fowling-pieces, and with a horſe or two let them coaſt up and down: this may do good, that they may not be ſo abuſed as I have ſhewn, but if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion bee, may follow on to purpoſe; and this is my advice proceeding from experience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95468:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Divers Inſtructions for the <hi>Inn-keeper,</hi> how to know Thieves from his honeſt Gueſts.</head>
                  <p>THus have I traced them from their firſt entrance to their action, and from their action to their flight, and I hope therein given ſo clear light to thoſe that deſire their apprehenſion, that yet may occaſion either their Converſion, or Impriſonment, and that their Conviction; and having ſpoke ſufficiently unto the Travilor to be carefull in his carriage in each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: Give me leave to add a word unto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Inn-keeper, that ſo he may diſcern between the honeſt Travilor and the Thief, which I ſhall perform in a word; which to doe, let him make it his chiefeſt care not to wink at ſuch diſhoneſty for hope of gain, leaſt that ſweet be imbittered by futer trouble and diſgrace: therefore let thy reſpects, who ever thou art that reads in this, be levelled at honeſty more then gain, knowing that a certain little with a godly peace of contentment, is a greater gain, and a higher hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, then an uncertain deal with a terrour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And to diſcover them is eaſie, if you obſerve my Rules.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, let the Oſtler obſerve and he ſhall diſcern their extraordinary curioſity about their Horſes, they muſt be ſtrangely dreſt, and as ſtrangely fed, with maſhes, bread, and mingled provender, and that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95468:21"/>in an unuſuall quantity; and if he wonder at this, they cannot forbear but praiſe their Tricks, and ſhew how by their good abilities they doe deſerve it, and ſometimes they will boaſt their worthy ſervices will ſoon repay the coſt, or ſome dark words to that effect, that are palpable grounds for to ſuſpect them; and then they will ask, whoſe Horſe is that, and what is the owner, that ſtands there? what function is their Maſter? what manner of men? whither they travell, how far, and when? So by his anſwer they ſurmiſe which will be the riche?ſt purchaſe.</p>
                  <p>And, ſecondly, if you not their Clokebags, they are empty, onely they carry them to make aſhew.</p>
                  <p>And then thirdly, when the Chamberlain has uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured them to their Chamber, he ſtrait is ſent away; but let him hearken, and if they are ſurely Thieves, tis ten to one, but they fall of ſhare what prize they have got that day, and let him prie narrowly into their Chamber and he ſhall ſee them ſhare as well as hear the money, and every one ſhall take what is his lot; this they never defer, if they have had any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, leſt he that hath the purſe ſhould cheat the reſt; this done, they hug each other, and then they knock in haſt, complaining at his negligence that ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and call for Sack, and then they want my Hoſts company, whom with the higheſt ſtrain of Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ſalute and bid him welcome; but if my Hoſt mark their diſcourſe, he may conjecture much, and know what men they are, as alſo by the ſaucy carriage of their men; and if their ſeverall Names you do inquire, injoyn your ſervants to doe the like, and you ſhall ſoon perceive they have more Names
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95468:21"/>then one a piece; and when they are at ſupper let ſome one haſtily knock at your gate, and bid him that attends obſerve their carriage then, and he ſhall ſee them ſtart, as in a fearfull maze, and ſtare each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the face with gaſtly looks, and if you are in the Chamber, ask what Officers are thoſe? who doe they look for? Or if forth from them, ask aloud that they may hear, what would Mr. Conſtable have? who doth he ſeek? or what is the Conſtable mad to knock ſo haſtily, or the like: and if they Weem much frighted, bid them not fear, none ſhall come up or offer him that wrong to ſearch his houſe, ſo to diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him, for he was no gueſts but honeſt Gentlemen, and if they command him, he will uſe his authority that none ſhall enter; there by this you may prie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their private thoughts ſo far, that they will confeſs ſomething, and reply, they ſhall be much ingaged for your ſuccour, and then you may uſe your own diſcretion.</p>
                  <p>And you may ſee by their needleſſe ſtay, their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard of time, what they expect, for they but bait to ſtand and gaze what purchaſe they can ſee go by, and when they have ſpied a likely money booty paſſe by them, they pretehd immediate buſineſſe calls them to be gone.</p>
                  <p>And when they come to take up Inne to lodge, they commonly come in divided, and come in ſeveral companies, to fruſtrate the Hue and Cry as to their number: beſides if one part be ſurprized the other may eſcape; and when the reſidue comes in, they ſeem as ſtrangers, and of mine Hoſt they will enquire what their Companions are, and what Country-men,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95468:22"/>whether he know them; and if they find he hair a jealouſie or ſuſpect either to them, they will preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will ſome buſineſſe to be gone with ſpeed: but if for honeſt Travilers you take them, as it is like you may, in your kitchen they doe meet by ſeeming chance, they as mear ſtrangers one another ſalute, and drinking there together ere they part they become familiarly acquainted and conclude to ſup together, when if you mark them well you ſhall find by their behavior that they are not ſtrangers but boſome friends, there they imbrace, rejoyce, and praiſe their plot, and laugh at mine Hoſt, that he ſuſpect them not. The faireſt Innes they uſually frequent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming that they will not ſo much diſparage mine Hoſt, as to make ſearch among his gueſts, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are perſons of account.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I laid open their deviſes and deceits, that ſo the honeſt traveller maueſcape their hand, and then fall into the hands of juſtice, thereby indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to repaire the wrongs my Country hath ſuffered, by indeavouring to prevent others from living in the like ſin, and ſo ſubvert ſin that would raiſe its own dominion by their fall and ruine; to which end that it may become effectuall, the Lord aſſiſt my indeavours to diſcover, and others by this diſcovery to apprehend them, and that apprehenſion expoſe them to the Law of juſtice, if they reject the Law of mercy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95468:22"/>
                  <head>Some Obſervations of the <hi>Hector</hi> and his <hi>Rum-Mort.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Dammce Captain</hi> by his Wit, Sword, and Baskethilt-Oathes; the two laſt he makes uſe of to frighten <hi>Rum-Cullies</hi> out of their caſh: As Horſes get their livings by their backs, as Swine and Women live for their fleſh, ſo this Creature lives by his wits; for what ſhould he do? he hath neither Lands nor Mannors but what lies commonly in a croſſe-way, yet he makes <hi>London</hi> (by a new denomination called <hi>Fools-Paradiſe</hi>) his Tenement, from which he receives good round ſummes of money for rent. And thus he doth it, he is excellently well skill'd in all kind of gaming, and all the cheats belonging to them; he frequents Bowling-greens, Boards-end, Billiards; as for Cards and Dice, thoſe are the chief inſtruments of his trade, which he continually carries about him; his Antagoniſt in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a Brother, and therefo e they play booty, that they may go half-ſnipps for the Bets. <hi>Hide-park</hi> is his <hi>Mart,</hi> in which he often ſels a younger Brother a little wit, at a very dear rate, in racing, wenching, &amp;c. Sometimes he betakes himſelf to what he hath a long time practiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> the Art of borrowing of any <hi>believing</hi> Creature, which he intends never to repay, and this he uſually brings to paſſe, for having a ſmooth tongue he will prate (when he thinks there is any good to be done) faſter then five Barbers, and ſo many Taylors; ſwear more then any Car-man, and lie nimbler then a City Tradeſman. If he hath ſpen but two ſhillings in a Tavern, he will the next time indeavour to be truſted in it, which if they refuſe, he will go near to <hi>inſconce</hi> the reckoning for that time, beſides the carrying away a <hi>Cup too much</hi> or ſo. He can likewiſe (if occaſion ſerve) <hi>Hack</hi> and <hi>Pad,</hi> not regarding how much he ſets his Country on the ſcore for it. But that which ſtands him in moſt ſtead is his Whore, whom he cals his Wife, by which he pretends ſtrange things to him he <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rapans,</hi> for they both agree together and comply, how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their deſign: Her part is to pick up a <hi>Dick</hi> that is full of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95468:23"/>money, whom ſhe invites to her houſe, being there, ſhe ſoon inticeth him to her imbracements, and when ſhe obſerves <hi>Rem in Ree,</hi> then ſhe thinks it high time to give her <hi>Hector</hi> notice of it, by dropping her ſlipper, or falling a bed-ſtaffe; he ſoon receives the alarum, being before prepared for it; up he comes (with an aſſiſtant) with fire darting through their eyes, belching and tumbling out Oaths faſter then a <hi>Iuggler</hi> puls Ribband out of his month, and then makes at them, as if they intended to kill them both, for the abuſe done them, one being the Husband, the other the Brother of this deceitful Quean: In fine, they threaten ſo long, till oft-times they crown their deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> to fleece the <hi>Cully</hi> of his money, and if that doth not ſuffice, enter him into Bond for more.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Hec.</hi> the <hi>Whore,</hi> and the <hi>Doctor</hi> are three,</l>
                     <l>Which can't drive a Trade unleſs they agree:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Whore</hi> drives the Trade, the <hi>Hec.</hi> is her man;</l>
                     <l>Yet both do combine to fleece whom they can.</l>
                     <l>Now if ſhe be <hi>clapt</hi> by trading too much;</l>
                     <l>Leaſt that ſhe ſhould break, the <hi>Doctor</hi> takes pain</l>
                     <l>To vamp her anew, ſo upſets her again.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Therefore I ſhall conclude with this; after he hath run in debt by all wayes that can be imagined, and cheated by all meanes that can be invented, then is he in continual fear and danger of priſon; if he chance to be taken, his utmoſt ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be baild out again, which he fears not, as long as his wits keep him company, by which its uſual for him to rid fooles out of priſon eight times in ten weeks. This rather perſwades then diſſwades him from his debauchments, for rather then he would leave them, he had rather die of the Pox in a Bawdy-houſe, or patiently walk down into a Vintners Cellar and drown himſelf in a Pipe of Sack. Thus have I briefly characterized him, who ſeldome ſpeaks what he meanes, performes nothing what he promiſeth, payes nothing what he owes, ſpeaks ſeldom without an Oath, lives without health in his bones, and dies without repentance</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95468:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
